Introduction to R

An introduction to R using R Markdown is provided here. The content is identical to the Intro to R wiki, which employs a basic R script.

The object of this document is to help you starting to use the R environment for statistical analysis and graphics.
You can read and follow the the text. Meanwhile you can copy the commands included into the frames part of this document, and paste them into an interactive R session.
Once you are familiar with the general functioning of R and of R's objects you can further advance in learning R with online manuals and guides. There is a great variety of documentation available at:

www.r-project.org.

http://www.statmethods.net/index.html

http://wiki.r-project.org/rwiki/doku.php

As well efficacious learning tools we would recommend that the user experiment with commands by, for example, trying different options to those stated. This experimentation is an important part of learning R using this synthetic document.

Starting R, getting help, stopping R

Start R

from a shell window type

R

In the bash terminal the following text will appear:

R version 2.10.0 (2009-10-26)
Copyright (C) 2009 The R Foundation for Statistical Computing
ISBN 3-900051-07-0
R is free software and comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY.
You are welcome to redistribute it under certain conditions.
Type 'license()' or 'licence()' for distribution details.
Natural language support but running in an English locale\\
R is a collaborative project with many contributors.
Type 'contributors()' for more information and
'citation()' on how to cite R or R packages in publications.
Type 'demo()' for some demos, 'help()' for on-line help, or
'help.start()' for an HTML browser interface to help.
Type 'q()' to quit R.

the > sign and the following blinking cursor is advising you are in the R environment. If you like, enter in administrative mode type sudo R and you will be able to install packages

stefano@stefano-linux:~\$ sudo R

basic_r.Rmd

---
title: "Introduction to R"
output:
  pdf_document: default
  html_document: default
---
 
---
 
### Getting help
 
R provides help with function and commands. On-line help gives useful information as well. Getting used to R help is key to successful statistical modelling. The online help can be accessed in HTML format by typing:
 
```{r}
help.start()
```
 
A keyword search is possible using the Search Engine and Keywords link. You can also use the help() or ? functions. For example, if we want to know how to use the matrix() function, the following two commands are equivalents:
 
```{r}
help(matrix)
? matrix
```
 
The `str(object.name)` command is used to display the internal structure of an R object. The `summary(object.name)` command gives a summary of an object, usually a statistical summary but it is generic meaning it has different operations for different classes of object.
 
```{r}  
dir() #  show files in the current directory
ls.str() # str() for each variable in the search path
getwd() #  is asking for the current working directory
```
 
When you quit, R will ask you if you want to save the workspace (that is, all of the variables you have defined in this session). Say “no” in order to avoid clutter.
 
Should an R command seem to be stuck or take longer than you’re willing to wait, type Control-C
 
---
 
### Calling Linux shell scripting commands 
 
`system("...")` is used to call any linux scripting commands within the R environment
 
```{r}  
system("pwd")
 
# is equivalent to
 
getwd()
```
 
---
 
### Inputs and outputs
 
Once you have opened an R session and eventually loaded the library you need, you can start exploring your data
 
*Loading data*
 
`load(file.name)` function, loads R type datasets written with the save function 
 
*Saving data*
 
`save(object.name.1, object.name.2, ... )` function save the specified object in XDR platform independent binary format
 
*Reading tables*
 
`read.table("filename")` Reads a file in table format and creates a data frame from it, with cases corresponding to lines and variables to fields within the file. Some useful arguments when reading in data are:
 
  * The default separator `sep = ""` is any whitespace. You might need  `sep = ","`  or  `";"`  and so on. 
  * Use `header = TRUE`  to read the first line as a header of column names. 
  * The `as.is = TRUE` specification is used to prevent character vectors from being converted to factors. 
  * The `comment.char = ""` specification is used to prevent "#" from being interpreted as a comment and use `skip = n` to skip n lines before reading data.
 
For more details:
 
```{r}
?read.table
```
 
Example:
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
landuse04 <- read.csv("~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/inputs/2004_landuse.csv", header=TRUE, sep=",", dec=".", na.string=":")
```
 
  * `read.csv("filename")` :  Used to read comma separated value (CSV) files. 
  * `read.delim("filename")` :  Used for reading tab-delimited files
  * `read.fwf()` :   reads a table of fixed width formatted data into a ’data.frame’; widths is an integer vector, giving the widths of the fixed-width fields
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
read.csv(file.name, header = TRUE, sep = ",", quote="\"", dec=".", fill =TRUE,  comment.char="", ...)
```
 
 
*Show variables and data in your workspace*
 
The list function ls() outputs a list of existing R objects
 
```{r}
ls()
```
 
The structure function `str(object.name)` informs you of the structure of a specific object.
The summary function `summary(object.name)` informs you of basic statistics of a specific object.
 
*Save and remove data or R objects*
 
`save(file, ...)` saves the specified objects (...) in the XDR platform-independent binary format.
 
Example:
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
save(landuse04, file="~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004")
```
 
`save.image(file)` saves all objects.
 
Example:
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
save(file="~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004_and_more")
```
 
`rm(file, ...)` removes the object you created or data you uploaded.
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
rm(landuse04)
```
 
No objects are present in memory now, use the `ls()` function to check it.
 
```{r}
ls()
```
 
 
But since you saved the landuse2004 data you can reload it using the `load()` function and check its structrure using the `str()` function.
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
load("~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004")
str(landuse04) # as a result you will see the following information:
```
 
---
 
### Variables and calculations
 
R has an interactive calculations function. The command is executed and results are displayed.
R uses: `+`, `-`, `/`, and `^` for addition, subtraction, multiplication, division and exponentiation, respectively.
 
```{r}
2+2
```
 
The [1] at the beginning of the line is just R printing an index of element numbers. If you print a result that appears on multiple lines, R will put an index at the beginning of each line.
 
```{r}
2*5
```
 
```{r}
10/2
```
 
```{r}
2*5
```
 
```{r}
2^3
```
 
*Variable settings*
 
You can simply create a variable by typing: `variable name = function, constant or calculation`.  
 
```{r}
x = 3*2
```
 
The results of 3*2 is not displayed. In fact, the `x` variable value is stored in the memory without printing it. To display the `x` value you can use: 
 
```{r}
print(x) 
 
# or 
 
x
```
 
Most users apply a similar syntax using the `<-` character string instead of the `=` character.
 
```{r} 
x <- 3
x
```
 
Also remember that R is case sensitive, print(X) or X is different from x. For instance
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
a <- 3
a
A
```
 
Variable names in R must begin with a letter, followed by alphanumeric characters. 
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
3e <- 2
```
 
In long names you can use `.` or `_` as in:
 
`very.long.variable.name.X` or `very_long_variable_name_Y`. 
 
But you can’t use blank spaces in variable names. 
 
Some schools of R users frown upon use of `.` in variable names, as the `.` has a special meaning in some functions. Using an underscore is a safer bet.
 
Avoid single letter names such us: c, l, q, t, C, D, F, I, and T, which are either built-in R functions or hard to tell apart.
 
```{r}
very_long_variable_name_X3 <- 3
very_long_variable_name_X3
```  
 
*Interactive calculations*
 
Once defined,  you can use variables in interactive calculations :
 
```{r} 
b = 2*2
a = 2*3
a*b
```
 
And you can use variables in formulas:
 
```{r}
c = 60 /(a+b)
c
```
 
Typing `a;b` you can display a and b variables at the same time:
 
```{r} 
a;b
```
 
If you forget to close a parentheses (in an R script or the console), R will display a `+` sign. In R Markdown, it will give an error.
 
For example, try running `c = 60 /(a+b` in the console.
 
In this case you can either close the parenthesis in the next line or type ctrl + c to go back to a new starting prompt. 
 
*Order of operations*
 
When using more complex formulas be aware of the importance of the order of operators. Parenthesis have priority over exponentiation, or powers, then comes multiplication and division, finally addition and subtraction. The following command:
 
```{r} 
C = ((a + 2 * sqrt(b))/(a + 8 * sqrt(b)))/2
C
 
# Is different from:
 
C = a + 2 * sqrt(b) / a + 8 * sqrt(b) / 2
C
```
 
As well as 
 
```{r}
100-40/2^4
 
# versus
 
(100-40)/2^4 
```
 
And:
 
```{r}
  -2^4
 
# is different from: 
 
 (-2)^4
```
 
---
 
### Logical values
 
R can perform conditional tests and generate True or False values as results. The logical operators are `<`, `<=`, `>`, `>=`, `==` for exact equality and `!=` for inequality. 
 
```{r}
x = 60
x > 100
 
x == 70
 
x > 3
 
x != 100
```
 
Logical values can be stored as variables: 
 
```{r}  
x <- 60
logical_value <- x >  3
logical_value
```
 
 
In addition if `c1` and `c2` are logical expressions, then `c1 & c2` is their intersection (“and”), `c1 | c2` is their union (“or”), and `!c1` is the negation of c1. 
 
---
 
### R objects
 
The entities R operates on are technically known as  objects. Examples are:
 
  * __vectors of numeric__ (real) or __complex values__, 
  * __vectors of logical__ values, and 
  * __vectors of character strings__. 
 
These are known as  “atomic”  structures since their components are all of the same type, or mode, namely numeric, complex, logical, character and raw.
 
R also operates on objects called __lists__, which are of mode list. These are ordered sequences of objects which individually can be of any mode. Lists are known as  “recursive”  rather than atomic structures since their components can themselves be lists in their own right.
 
The other recursive structures are those of mode __function__ and __expression__. Functions are the objects that form part of the R system along with similar user written functions, which we will discuss in some detail later. Expressions as objects form an advanced part of R which will not be discussed in this guide, except indirectly when we discuss formulae used with modeling in R.
 
By the __mode__ of an object we mean the basic type of its fundamental constituents. This is a special case of a  “property”  of an object. Another property of every object is its __length__. The functions `mode(object)` and `length(object)` can be used to find out the mode and length of any defined structure 10.
 
Further properties of an object are usually provided by `attributes(object)`, (see 'Getting and setting attributes'). Because of this, mode and length are also called “intrinsic attributes” of an object. For example, if z is a complex vector of length 100, then in an expression mode(z) is the character string "complex" and length(z) is 100.
 
---
 
### Vectors
 
Vectors are combinations of scalars in a string structure. Vectors must have all values of the same mode. Thus any given vector must be unambiguously either logical, numeric, complex, character or raw. (The only apparent exception to this rule is the special “value” listed as `NA` for quantities not available, but in fact there are several types of NA). Note that a vector can be empty and still have a mode. For example the empty character string vector is listed as character(0) and the empty numeric vector as numeric(0). 
 
`c(...)`  is the generic function to combine arguments with the default forming a vector. Using the `RECURSIVE=TRUE` option allows one to descend through lists combining all elements into one vector.
 
To see details for the generic function c(...) and combine arguments forming a vector: 
 
```{r}  
? c 
```
 
As an example we can create a simple vector of seven values typing: 
 
```{r}
c(2,3,4,5,10,5,8)
```
 
We can generate a sequence using the syntax `:`
 
```{r}  
1:10
```
 
We can generate the same sequence of 1:10 command using the `seq()` function. The syntax will be :
 
```{r}  
seq(1,10)
```
 
The `seq()` function `seq(from = number, to = number, by = number)` creates a vector starting from a value to another by a defined increment:
 
```{r}
seq(1, 10, 0.25)
 
seq(from = 1, to = 10, by =  0.25)
```
 
 
The replicate function `rep(x, n)`  enables you to replicate a vector several times in a more complex vector. 
Calculations can be included to form vectors as well and functions can be combined in the same command:
 
```{r}
oneTwoThree <- 1:3
 
rep(oneTwoThree, 10)
 
c(10*0:10)
 
rep(c (5*40:1, 5*1:40, 5, 6, 7, 8, 3, 2001:2014), 2)
 
rep(seq(1, 3, 0.5), 3)
```
 
---
 
### Missing Values
 
In some cases the components of a vector or of an R object in general may not be completely known. When an element or value is “not available” or is a “missing value” in the statistical sense, a place within a vector may be reserved for it by assigning it the special value `NA`. 
 
Any operation on an `NA` becomes an `NA`. 
 
The function `is.na(x)` gives a logical vector of the same size as x with value `TRUE` if and only if the corresponding element in x is `NA`.
 
```{r}
z <- c(1:3, NA)
ind <- is.na(z)
ind
```
 
There is a second kind of “missing” values which are produced by numerical computation, the so-called "Not a Number", `NaN`, values. Examples are `0/0` or `Inf - Inf` which both give `NaN` since the result cannot be defined sensibly.
 
```{r}
Inf-Inf
 
0/0
```
 
In summary, `is.na(xx)` is TRUE both for `NA` and `NaN` values. To differentiate these, `is.nan(xx)` is only TRUE for NaNs. Missing values are sometimes printed as <NA> when character vectors are printed without quotes.
 
```{r}
z <- c(1:3,NA)
 
is_not_available <- is.na(z) 
is_not_a_number <- is.nan(z)
 
is_not_a_number
is_not_available
```
 
---
 
### Matrices
 
Matrices, or more generally arrays, are multi-dimensional generalizations of vectors. In fact, they are vectors that can be indexed by two or more indices and will be printed in a special way. See Arrays and matrices.
 
  * Factors provide compact ways to handle categorical data. See Factors.
  * Lists are a general form of vector in which the various elements need not be of the same type, and are often themselves vectors or lists. Lists provide a convenient way to return the results of a statistical computation. See Lists.
 
The `matrix()` function creates a matrix from the given set of values. We use the `matrix(x, nrow=, ncol=)` function to set the matrix cell values, the number of rows and the number of columns. We can use the `colnames()` and `rownames()` functions to set the column and row names of the matrix-like object.
 
```{r}
matrix(data = NA, nrow = 2, ncol = 3) 
example_matrix <- matrix(0,2,3)
example_matrix
 
example_matrix[1,]
 
example_matrix[,2]
 
example_matrix[1,] <- 1:3
example_matrix[2,] <- c(5,10,4)
example_matrix
 
matrix_head <- c("col a","col b","column c")
matrix_side <- c("first raw","second raw")
str(matrix_side)
 
```
When using `" "` we create and refer to a character type `chr` input
 
```{r}
numeric_vector <- c(rep(c (5*10:1, 5, 6), 2))
character_vector <- as.character(numeric_vector)
str(character_vector)
 
colnames(example_matrix) <- matrix_head
rownames(example_matrix) <- matrix_side
example_matrix
 
str(example_matrix)
```
 
---
 
### Arrays
An array can be considered a multiple subscripted collection of data entries, for example numeric. R allows simple facilities for creating and handling arrays, and in particular the special case of matrices. 
 
As well as giving a vector structure a `dim` attribute, arrays can be constructed from vectors by the array function, which has the form `array(data_vector, dim_vector)`
 
```{r}
Z <- array(1:24, c(3,4,2))
Z
```
 
---
 
### Data Frames
 
Data frames are matrix-like structures, in which the columns can be of different types. Think of data frames as  data matrices  with one row per observational unit but with (possibly) both numerical and categorical variables. Many experiments are best described by data frames: the treatments are categorical but the response is numeric.
 
As a result R dataframes are tightly coupled collections of variables which share many of the properties of matrices and of lists. Data frames are used as the fundamental data structure by most of R's modeling software.
A data frame is a list with class "data.frame". There are restrictions on lists that may be made into data frames, namely:
 
  * The components must be vectors (numeric, character, or logical), factors, numeric matrices, lists, or other data frames.
  * Matrices, lists, and data frames provide as many variables to the new data frame as they have columns, elements, or variables, respectively.
  * Numeric vectors, logicals and factors are included, and character vectors are coerced to be factors, whose levels are the unique values appearing in the vector.
  * Vector structures appearing as variables of the data frame must all have the same length, and matrix structures must all have the same row size. 
 
See:
 
```{r} 
? data.frame
```
 
To construct a dataframe:
 
```{r}
my_data_frame = data.frame(v=1:4,ch=c("a","b","c","d"),n=10)
my_data_frame
```
 
Or:
 
```{r}
my_data_frame = data.frame(vector = 1:4, 
                         character = c("a","b","c","d"),
                         const.vector = 10,
                         row.names = c("data1","data2","data3","data4"))
my_data_frame
```
 
---
 
### Data selection and manipulation
 
You can extract data from dataframes using the    `[ [    ] ]`  and  `$`  sign:
 
```{r}
my_data_frame[["character"]]
```
 
```{r}
my_data_frame[[2]]
```
 
Call the 3rd value of the character vector :
 
```{r}
my_data_frame[[2]][3]
```
 
Or using the `$` syntax:
 
```{r}
my_data_frame$vector
```
 
```{r}
my_data_frame$character[2:3]
```
 
You can add single arguments to a data frame, query information, select and manipulate arguments or single values from a dataframe 
 
```{r}
my_data_frame$new
```
 
```{r}
my_data_frame$new = c(10,11,20,40)
my_data_frame
```
 
```{r}
str(my_data_frame)
```
 
`length(object.name)` will return the number of elements in an object such as a matrix vector or dataframes:
 
```{r}
length(my_data_frame$new) 
```
 
`which(object.name)` and  `which.max(object.name)` return the index of a specific or of the greatest element of an object.
 
```{r}    
which.max(my_data_frame$new) 
```
 
```{r}
which(my_data_frame$new==20) 
```
 
`max(object.name)` will return the value of the greatest element.
 
```{r}  
max(my_data_frame$new) 
```
 
`sort(object.name)`` will sort from small to big:
 
```{r}  
sort(my_data_frame$new)
```
 
`rev(object.name)` from big to small:
 
```{r}
rev(sort(my_data_frame$new)) 
```
 
`subset(object.name, ...)` -- the subset function returns a selection of an R-object with respect to criteria (typically comparisons: x$V1 < 10). If the R-object is a data frame, the option `select` gives the variables to be kept or dropped using a minus sign.
 
```{r}
subset(my_data_frame, my_data_frame$new == 20)
```
 
We can use the `sample()` function to sample from a vector or set of values
 
```{r}
sample(my_data_frame$new, 3)
```
 
```{r}
sample(my_data_frame$new, 3)
```
 
```{r}
sample(my_data_frame$new, 3)
```
 
---
 
###  More examples
 
The following R commands give an example of the simple procedure of:
 
  1. Importing data, 
  2. Cleaning a table by extracting relevant information, and 
  3. Checking the presence of missing data.
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
landuse04 <- read.csv("~/ost4sem/studycase/Lab_scripts/inputs/2004_landuse.csv", 
                    header = TRUE, sep = ",", dec = ".", na.string = ":")
 
forests04 <- subset(landuse04, landuse04$forest.Wooded.area >= 0 )
forests04$landuse <- NULL
forests04_check <- na.fail(forests04)
forests04$total.Total.area[1] <- NA
forests04_check <- na.fail(forests04)
```
 
You will find that the last line fails given missing values in the dataset.
 
We can resolve the situation at the beginning with no NA
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}
forests04 <- subset(landuse04, landuse04$forest.Wooded.area >=0 )
forests04$landuse <- NULL
forests04_check <- na.fail(forests04)
str(forests04)
```
 
Do you see something strange? look at the `forests04$geographic.Unit` level of factors and the dataframe number of variables!
 
Let's fix it now!
 
```{r, eval = FALSE}  
library(gdata)
forests04 <- drop.levels(forests04)
str(forests04)
```
 
---
 
### Functions 
 
Functions are themselves objects in R which can be stored in the project's workspace. This provides a simple and convenient way to extend R.  
 
Usage: in writing your own function you provide one or more arguments or names for the function, an expression (or body of the function) and a value is produced equal to the output function result
 
`function(arglist) expr   function definition`
`return(value)`
 
Example:
 
```{r}
myfunction <- function(x) x^5
myfunction(3)
```
 
```{r}
body(myfunction) <- quote(5^x)
```
 
Or equivalently
 
```{r}
body(myfunction) <- expression(5^x)
myfunction(3) 
```
 
```{r}
body(myfunction)
5^x
myfunction
```

Hands-on GRASS: First steps

The object of this page is to start using Grass and to get familiar with some general GIS operations. We are going to use a command line approach. This is to enable carrying out stand-alone processes in the future, and understand step by step each function and the options per function which are available. Let´s start using grass.

download the script or VM@: ~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_grass/basic_grass.sh

Starting Grass

Every Grass project has a predefined data structure

GISDBASE - Grass data are stored in a directory referred to as a DATABASE “GISDBASE”. This directory has to be created with mkdir or a file manager, before starting to work with GRASS. Within this DATABASE, the projects are organized by project areas stored in subdirectories called LOCATIONs.

LOCATION - A Location is defined by its coordinate system, map projection and geographical boundaries. The subdirectories and files defining a LOCATION are created automatically when GRASS is started for the first time with a new LOCATION.

MAPSET - Locations can have many MAPSETs. Each MAPSET is a LOCATION's subdirectory. A new MAPSET can be added at GRASS startup.

A common problem of basic users is not really using grass but starting a grass section. The main reason is due to the grass data structure and the way a grass section has to be set up before starting!

To remove a MAPSET, remove it's directory using your file manager or by

rm -rf /path/./mapsettodelete The wxGUI graphical user interface provides options to rename/remove LOCATIONs and MAPSETs.

There are several ways to use and open Grass. The simplest way is to open a terminal and type: grass72 -gui

A second option is to use the Python GUI by typing in the terminal:

grass72 -wxpython

the Graphical User Interface GUI will ask you to define the GISDBASE, LOCATION and MAPSET to use. If you want you can select the Location wizard to create a new location with newest projection parameters or the Create mapset button to create a new mapset inside a pre-existing location.

To enter grass in command line:

 grass72 -text ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe/PERMANENT

Using the above command line we have already entered into the Grass environment with the GISDBASE, LOCATION and MAPSET defined by the ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe/PCEM path

Once you are running Grass through the bash shell terminal you can always start the graphical user interface with:

 g.gui wxpython &

GRASS COMMAND STRUCTURE

prefix | function | class type of command | example
d.* | display | graphical output | d.rast: views raster map
| | | d.vect: views vector map
db.* | database | database management | db.select: selects value(s) from table
g.* | general | general file operations | g.rename: renames map
i.* | imagery | image processing | i.smap: image classifier
ps.* | postscript | map creation format | ps.map: map creation in Postscript
r.* | raster | raster data processing | r.buffer: buffer around raster features
r.mapcalc: map algebra
r3.* | voxel | raster voxel data processing | r3.mapcalc: volume map algebra
v.* | vector | vector data processing | v.overlay: vector map intersections

For detailed instructions on grass command syntax and use, go to the GRASSonline manual or type man and function name. As an example

man r.info

Grass working environment

The g.gisenv command informs you of your current grass environment settings

 g.gisenv

If you started grass correctly you should visualize the following lines on your terminal

GISDBASE=/home/user/ost4sem/grassdb
LOCATION_NAME=europe
MAPSET=PERMANENT
MONITOR=x2
GRASS_GUI=text
GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~ > 

Running grass through the bash shell terminal allows you to use all command line functionality of both grass and shell. As an example you can type

ls

and visualize all files available in your shell current working directory. This means that all your output files produced by bash command lines functionality will be saved in the current working directory (if not specified differently). Many non-geographical grass output features such as text file reports or images will be saved as well in the current working directory. The GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~ > inform you are currently working in the home folder. See

pwd

for double checking the same information using a bash command instead of the grass g.gisenv command.

It is a good working habit within Grass to set bash shell working directory the same as your GRASS LOCATION folder.

cd ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe/

On the terminal you will no longer see

 GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~ >

but
GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe > and you will be aware tif your current bash shell working directory match your grass location directory.

Grass MAPSET

We have explained that grass projects can be organised in MAPSETs by users, by themes, by extent or locations, and grouped within the same grass LOCATION. This LOCATION will group several MAPSETS defined by a common projection and is able to access a common set of maps in the PERMANENT MAPSET forlder. When we work in a specific MAPSET we will have no rights to write or delete maps in a different MAPSET. For doing so you will have to change your working MAPSET directory and then delete or produce new maps.

The g.mapset command allows you to change the Grass working directory and successively generate, delete or modify maps as you wish.

g.mapset -l
g.mapset mapset=PCEM
g.gisenv 

Now you should see the following settings:

GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe > g.gisenv
GISDBASE=/home/user/ost4sem/grassdb
LOCATION_NAME=europe
MAPSET=PCEM
MONITOR=x2
GRASS_GUI=text
GRASS 7.0.0 (europe):~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe >

From grass 6.3 only the -c flag creates a new mapset if it doesn't exist.; -l List available mapsets (!)

Manage maps

To list your available maps:

g.list type=vect -p
g.list vect  -p
g.list rast -p

The user can add, modify, and delete data layers that exist under his current mapset. Although the user can also access (i.e., use) data that are stored under other mapsets in the same GRASS location, the user can only make permanent changes (create or modify data) located in the current mapset. To access maps in a different current mapset we use the addmapset option in the g.mapset function. As an example:

g.mapsets mapset=Vmodel operation=add

Now we can access the Vmodel mapset and eventually copy a map from the Vmodel mapset to our current mapset directory using the g.copy function:

g.copy rast=potveg_ita@Vmodel,pvegita 
g.list rast -p

And delete a map with the g.remove command

g.remove -f type=rast name=pvegita
# g.remove rast=pvegita old syntax in grass 6.4
g.list rast

You can access but not delete or modify a map in a different mapset from your current

  g.remove -f type=rast name=potveg_europe@Vmodel
  g.remove -f type=rast name=potveg_europe

We have to be careful in Grass to understand the possible differences existing in the same MAPSET between the whole extent and resolution of the MAPSET itself, the extent, resolution and geographic location of our working region, and the extent and location of what we are visualising.

Region settings

In GRASS, a region refers to a geographic area with some defined boundaries, based on a specific map coordinate system and map projection. Grass region definition and details. This crucial Grass setting will allow us to define within MAPSET settings a particular region of work.
Once defined the grass region, grass modules (or programs) will operate within this region. The user can create, modify, and store as many geographic region definitions as desired for any given mapset. However, only one of these geographic region definitions will be current at any given moment, for a specified mapset. GRASS programs that respect the geographic region settings will use the current geographic region settings.

To query your current region settings type

 g.region -p
 

and to reset region settings to their original extent type

 g.region -d

-p stands for “print” ; -d stands for default

You can modify your default g. region with a -s flag within the PERMANENT directory.

Now we will define a new study area for the Scandinavia region.

g.region -p
g.region n=6015390 e=5676400 s=3303955 w=3876180 res=1000 save=scandinavia --overwrite
g.region -p

You will visualize the current and newest region settings saved as scandinavia

If you open Qgis

 qgis & 

You can load a raster map on Qgis from the menue: Plugin GRASS > add GRASS raster layer >

Gisdbase : /home/user/ost4sem/grassdb

Location : europe

Mapset : PERMANENT

Map name : fnfpc

If you click on “ Display current Grass region ” you will see the Scandinavia area within a red frame.

Back to GRASS if you reset the default grass region

g.region -d

And when you look again at Qgis, you can visualise the red frame changing position by clicking twice on “ Display current Grass region ”.

Clipping maps and changing resolution use

g.region allow us to do two basic GIS function: resample and clip.
We would like to have 3 new maps of forest/non-forest percentage clipped and resampled with a different resolution from a forest/non-forest map. The original forest/non-forest map has the European extent and 1km resolution. We need to generate:

Italian extent map at 20km resolution,

Alpine extent map at 10km resolution

Alpine and Carpathians extent map at 5km reslution.

In the europe LOCATION different g.region exists:

ls PERMANENT/windows/ 
ls */windows/

The g.region are saved in the following folders and named as follow:

EUforest/windows/: europe

PCEMstat/windows/: alpine

PCEM/windows/: alp_car

Vmodel/windows/: italy

PERMANENT/windows/: scandinavia

The Italian g.region is in Vmodel mapset, the Alpine and Carpathiens g.region is in PCEM mapset, and the Alpine region is in PCEMstat.

  g.region italy@Vmodel -p 
#projection: 99 (Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area)
#zone:       0
#datum:      ** unknown (default: WGS84) **
#ellipsoid:  grs80
#north:      2900000
#south:      1400000
#west:       3960000
#east:       5100000
#nsres:      1000
#ewres:      1000
#rows:       1500
#cols:       1140
#cells:      1710000

we see that the Italian g.region has 1km res and is 1500 x 1140 pixels

We now resample the g.region at 20km using the res=new_res option and will set 75 x 57 pixels of 20k resolution

  g.region res=20000 -p 
#  projection: 99 (Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area)
#  zone:       0
#  datum:      ** unknown (default: WGS84) **
#  ellipsoid:  grs80
#  north:      2900000
#  south:      1400000
#  west:       3960000
#  east:       5100000
#  nsres:      20000
#  ewres:      20000
#  rows:       75
#  cols:       57
#  cells:      4275

we can create a new forest/non-forest map with the new extent and resolution using r.mapcalc function r.mapcalc details

r.mapcalc "fnfpc_italy20k = fnfpc" 

Now create the two other maps:

  g.region alpine@PCEMstat res=10000 -p
#projection: 99 (Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area)
#zone:       0
#datum:      ** unknown (default: WGS84) **
#ellipsoid:  grs80
#north:      2751000
#south:      2310000
#west:       3960000
#east:       4700000
#nsres:      10022.72727273
#ewres:      10000
#rows:       44
#cols:       74
#cells:      3256
  r.mapcalc "fnfpc_alpine10k = fnfpc" 
 
  g.region alp_car@PCEM res=5000 -p
#projection: 99 (Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area)
#zone:       0
#datum:      ** unknown (default: WGS84) **
#ellipsoid:  grs80
#north:      3070000
#south:      2270000
#west:       3900000
#east:       5660000
#nsres:      5000
#ewres:      5000
#rows:       160
#cols:       352
#cells:      56320
  r.mapcalc "fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k = fnfpc" 

You can save a new extent and resolution as g.mapset with the save=namenew option

g.region alp_car@PCEM res=5000 -p save=alp_car_5km_res

Visualize maps

In the forest non forest map fnfpc each pixel value corresponds to ha of tree cover or percentage cover within each sq km pixel.
Lets visualise the map in different ways.

Qgis

The Qgis is a very simple and practical tools for visualising maps. Open Qgis and visualize the maps you just created: Plugin GRASS > add GRASS raster layer >

Gisdbase : /home/user/ost4sem/grassdb

Location : europe

Mapset : PERMANENT

Map name : fnfpcalpinecarpatien5k

GRASS GUI

Also grass has a GUI for vitalising maps. Open it and charge the maps just created

 g.gui tcltk     

Click on: add raster layer > Base map (select your maps and refresh the Map display window.

GRASS display monitor

In grass we can visualize maps in different monitors. To list available monitors, type:

 d.mon -l

We can open a monitor and display a raster

 g.region rast=fnfpc
 d.mon start=wx0
 d.rast fnfpc

and do the same thing for the other maps in different monitors

 d.mon start=wx1    
 d.rast fnfpc_alpine10k 

wrong vizualisation extent

 g.region rast=fnfpc_alpine10k 
 d.mon start=wx1    
 d.rast fnfpc_alpine10k 

 g.region rast=fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k
 d.mon start=x3
 d.rast fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k
 
 g.region rast=fnfpc_italy20k
 d.mon start=x4
 d.rast fnfpc_italy20k

And we can also change the resolution of the visualization

 g.region rast=fnfpc res=50000
 d.mon start=x5
 d.rast fnfpc

The following table give some general info on the display functions of GRASS:

Command | Action
d.mon start=x0 | Opens the terminal x0
d.mon stop=x0 | Closes the terminal x0
d.mon select=x0 | Selects the terminal x0
d.mon -l | Displays the list of available monitors
d.frame -e | Manages display frames on the user's graphics monitor
d.vect col=red | Displays and overlays vector map layers in the red color
d.rast | Displays and overlays raster map layers
d.m | Display manager for GRASS
d.what.vect | Allows the user to interactively query a vector map
d.legend | Displays a legend for a raster map

here is a detailed explanation and full list of d. modules

Let's have a look now at the Pinus cembra distribution map, downloaded from the Euforgen database

 
 g.region rast=pcem_euforgen
 d.mon start=wx1
 d.rast pcem_euforgen
 d.vect map=EUcountry@EUforest fcolor="none" col=red

Generating multiple maps with standardized settings

Lets rename our maps for simplification

g.copy rast=fnfpc,eu1 
g.copy rast=fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k,ac5 
g.copy rast=fnfpc_alpine10k,a10
g.copy rast=fnfpc_italy20k,i20

And remove rasters with old names

g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_alpine10k
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_italy20k

You can use the g.rename rast=oldname,newname function instead of g.copy and g.remove if you are dealing with maps in the same mapsets and you hgave rights to rename them

We also need to convert vector topology from grass 6 to grass 7 version

  g.copy vect=EUcountry@EUforest,EUcountry
  v.build.all

for map in a10 ac5 eu1 i20 ; do
 g.region rast=$map
 cat ~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_grass/green_palett_5class | r.colors map=$map  rules="-" 
 d.mon start=png 
 d.rast $map 
 d.vect map=EUcountry fcolor="none" color=red
 d.mon stop=png
 mv  map.png ~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_grass/output_map_$map.png
done 

below the whole procedure in a script to generate multiple maps with different resolution and extents.

- grass_basic.sh

grass -text ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe/PCEM
g.mapsets mapset=Vmodel operation=add
g.region n=6015390 e=5676400 s=3303955 w=3876180 res=1000 save=scandinavia --overwrite
g.region italy@Vmodel -p 
g.region res=20000 -p 
r.mapcalc "fnfpc_italy20k = fnfpc" --overwrite
g.region alpine@PCEMstat res=10000 -p
r.mapcalc "fnfpc_alpine10k = fnfpc" --overwrite
g.region alp_car@PCEM res=5000 -p
r.mapcalc "fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k = fnfpc" --overwrite
g.copy rast=fnfpc,eu1 
g.copy rast=fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k,ac5 
g.copy rast=fnfpc_alpine10k,a10
g.copy rast=fnfpc_italy20k,i20
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc 
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_alpine_carpatien5k 
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_alpine10k
g.remove -f type=raster name=fnfpc_italy20k
g.copy vect=EUcountry@EUforest,EUcountry
v.build.all
for map in a10 ac5 eu1 i20 ; do
 g.region rast=$map
 cat ~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_grass/green_palett_5class | r.colors map=$map  rules="-" 
 d.mon start=png 
 d.rast $map 
 d.vect map=EUcountry fcolor="none" color=red
 d.mon stop=png
 mv  map.png ~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_grass/output_map_$map.png
done